hi I'm coach Brett curas and uh this
video is going to address buttwink in
the squat and I've got Skelly here with
me um now this is uh not of the best uh
anatomical model of a skeleton I
actually got it at
Costco uh just knowing that I would need
to use it for a video one day so I've
had this guy for a couple months but
never used him uh until now so so this
is he's going to help out here um so
first let me describe what buttwink is
we in the field call it buttwink but it
buttwink really refers to his posterior
pelvic tilt so I have Skelly set up in
the front squat
position he's going to be going down
into a squat okay and as he goes down
there comes a point
where the pelvis will begin to postery
tilt
like this it will posteriorly rotate and
it pulls the lumbar spine with it in
flection and so if you were to look at
as he's going deep into the squat his
femurs are rising up like this he would
get to a point where he ran out of hip
range of
motion and from here forward going
deeper would just
be posteriorly tilting of the pelvis and
rounding of the low back and this is
dangerous so we always say keep an arch
when we say keep an arch this means keep
the spine like this don't let it round
like that so you don't want too much
rounding at the bottom of a squat
because you've got a a bar on your back
that's pushing down uh that creates
compressive force on the spine but what
most people don't realize about the SP
spinal loading is most of the
compressive force is created by muscles
you've got abdominal muscles that
connect you've got erector muscles that
connect and they when they contract
picture a muscle squeezing together it's
going to clamp down on that
spine and compress it so when you've got
compressive force and you have that
natural lordotic curve you can withstand
a lot of forces but round over and do
the same thing and you're risking
herniations and things like that and and
damaging certain
ligaments so you really want to control
this when you go down in a squat you
want to keep this Arch like this and you
don't want the pelvis to rotate too much
now here's the thing about Theory and
working in the field
um when when I squat um I can come down
I get to about right here and this is
where I start to lose my
tilt from here I can keep this nice
solid Arch when I go deeper I start to
lose it so that last few inches of range
of motion is where I lose my solid
lumbar extension and my anterior pelvic
tilt however it's not it's not a problem
I can squat like
this month week in week out month in
month out year in year out and it
doesn't cause a problem because it's not
too much lumbar flexion it's not too
much posterior pelvic toe
so I get so many emails where people say
well Brett you know first of all how do
I know if
I'm having too much buttwink or too much
postor pelvic tilt or lumbar flexion at
the bottom of squat and this is where
the art of coaching comes into play
because you just as a coach I've seen it
for so many years you just know there
are some guys I've seen the worst case
was a guy in uh Auckland that I that I
used to train with he would get to about
I'd say when he squatted he would get to
about
right here and he would start to lose
his he wouldn't even be close to
parallel and he would start to
round and he'd go like this and he'd
start to round over um if you can get
past parallel to here and keep this Arch
and then right about here you start
losing it and it's just a little bit
then it's okay so some some amount is
acceptable but excessive is too much
you've got a little bit of wiggle room
in the lumbar spine but not much and
that's again where the art comes into
play because I just know when I see it
and it's hard to explain you know if
they're using 20% of their lumbar spine
flexibility it's not as big of a deal if
they're going to full lumbar flexion and
you just know it when you see it but the
other question I get is how do you
improve it so I want to explain some
things about uh about the human body
here so all right most everyone thinks
it's it's a matter of increasing
flexibility so they will they
rationalize that if I go once I get to
here I run out
of flexibility in certain muscles and I
have tight hip flexors tight hamstrings
or whatever people think is tight and
this is causing me to round over I need
to you know it's these tight muscles are
pulling and it's causing me to round
over and I need to stretch those muscles
but let me explain some things real
quick um it's more likely due to one's
particular and again this is not the
best model of the human body but you can
see that the hip is a ball and socket
joint so when
I ideally you'd be like this skeleton
where you could just you know well not
ideally because if you could go back to
here that would be problematic the point
is you'd want good hip flexion and hip
extension Mobility you wouldn't be
restricted but as you can see in this
model I get to a point here I have no
more hip extension unless I really jar
things and so people have a natural hip
flexion uh you know a point at where it
kind of
stops and it's the way that the head of
the femur articulates with the
acetabulum here and the hip socket so if
you get to a point where this
stops it will pull I can't go any
further this way so the only way to go
deeper is by you know continuing to
round the pelvis and round the lumbar
spine with it because I can't go anymore
here and this depends on your own
Anatomy so some people who have good
Anatomy can go deeper maybe they can get
to here and some people can only go to
here so most of this is do Anatomy it's
anatomical and some cultures like Asians
for example are notorious for being a
all squat real deep and they keep that
because they they do that in their daily
lives they squat a lot when they eat and
things like that and then other cultures
um they for example you might may have
heard of the Scottish hip um or the
Celtic hip it's just common for like
Northern Europeans to have you know
deeper hip sockets and they might run
out of flexibility right before parallel
so the only way they're getting below
parallel in the squat is to butwink a
little bit now here's what's important
for you to understand people do improve
their hip flexion Mobility over time
people can improve their squat their
squat depth and let me first explain why
stretching isn't always the solution
people a lot of times talk about the
hamstrings now
if you think about the hamstrings um
they're the way they uh their attachment
points when I go down into a squat okay
I am going to be shortening the
hamstrings at the knee but lengthening
the hamstrings at the hip and so the net
result is that I don't get much length
change it might increase in length the
hamstrings might increase in length just
a little bit especially if you hold your
anterior pelvic tilt if the if the
pelvis is tilted properly but when I go
deep into a squat it's not my hamstrings
limiting my squat depth it's not tight
hamstrings that are preventing the hip
from going deeper into flexion because
they don't change length that much all
right now think about the hip flexors
you've got you know the iliacus here
you've got the soas here so the ilos
soaz when I go into hip flexion is
actually shortening it's not going to be
lengthening and if you think about the
rectus Fus the rectus Fus is going to be
lengthening at the knee but shortening
at the hip so just like the hamstrings
it's a biarticular muscle meaning it
crosses Two Joints so just like the
hamstrings it's not going to change
length much so it's probably not the hip
flexors that are and this is probably
the prevailing thought is that Butt Wink
is is caused by tight hip flexors and
you need to stretch your hip flexors and
it's automatically going to cure your
buttwink and you're going to have less
postor pelvic tilt but that's probably
not the issue either um so
stretching can help I'm not telling you
not to stretch but what I am telling you
is that motor control is imperative here
and let me explain this further when you
go down into a squat all
right you've got a lot of muscles here
that are going to be working working
right okay so you have the glutes you've
got the quads you've got the hammies
you've got the adductors you've got the
Erectors you've got the abdominals
you've got all these muscles that are
helping you Squat and as you gain
proficiency um you become a better
squatter now the first thing I will tell
you is see when this when Skelly squats
down he goes deep into a squat look at
how much ankle dorsiflexion Mobility he
has uh here his knees go way out if you
are limited in ankle dors flexion
Mobility let's say you can only go to
here your knees can only migrate forward
that much because you have tight uh
ankle Mobility ankle dorsiflexion
Mobility so he can't do this so if he
has to do this look at what happens to
his if I if I move the knee back like
this he would fall backwards the only
way to stay centered would be to round
over more so just tight that shows you
how just having tight uh ankle dorsa
flexors can cause people to round over
so that's the first thing that you need
to improve is ankle dors dorsal flexion
Mobility or a lot of Olympic
weightlifters have healed shoes where
it's like this so now that same see if I
can only get to here but then I use
heeled shoes see how that shifts the
knee forward and you can get more um
forward knee migration some bodybuilders
will stand on plates so that might help
solve the low back rounding and that's
not even addressing the hip that's
addressing the ankle but let's assume
you have good ankle dors of flexion
mobility and you can go down deep here's
what you need to
know some muscles here pull on the head
of the they they they act on the head of
the femur and they influence how it
artic articulates in with the hip socket
so since the glutes uh originate
posteriorly to the uh glal tuberosity
and the IT band when they contract they
exert a rearward pull and this creates
it keeps the head of the femur suctioned
into that acetabulum and it creates some
space for this to keep to allow because
if you're jamming forward you might your
hip flexion Mobility might stop here but
if the glutes are working properly it
can pull rearward and allow some more
space so this is why having properly
activating glutes is important but it's
not just the glutes it's all the muscles
acting in proper coordination so motor
control is kind of like you can think of
it as coordination so you have stability
you have mobility and you have motor
control Mobility is the ability of this
you know um of the joint to move through
a range of motion stability is the
ability of muscles to stabilize the you
know the joints but motor control is
where it programs everything together so
motor control is your coordination so as
you descend into a squat and you have
properly activating muscles the hip
flexors are working properly from this
end the adductors are working properly
from this end the quads are you know the
well the I already said that the rectus
florus is part of the hip flexor is
working properly the glutes are working
properly the hamstrings are working
properly the hip rotators are working
properly and you've got everything you
know the Erectors and the ABS are
stabilizing the the lumbar spine and
pelvis and then eventually your brain
learns out to program it all together
and suction that the the head of the
femur in place and keep it centrating in
that joint properly which allows for
greater depth and so a lot of times
times uh as you improve your squat you
gain experience with a squat and you
gain coordination you will improve your
uh hip flexion mobility and you will
cure that buttwink so it's not just
don't just stretch you also have to
practice practice squatting practice
squatting with lighter weights practice
goblet squatting and practice going deep
keeping that chest up and sinking down
and this will help improve your your hip
flexion Mobility over time make sure you
have good ankle dorsal flexion Mobility
make sure you have good core stability
and you know and as you increase your
hip mobility and your and you practice
the squat more you should be able to
improve your squat depth over time
without butt winking without losing that
spinal Arch however please realize that
it is very anatomically related so not
everyone is going to be able to sink a
rock bottom full squat uh
and that's up to you to determine which
is your best squat so some people should
probably only go to parallel what's the
point some
people some people might even not even
be able to go to parallel um and some
people can go rock bottom and that all
depends on your anatomy and your goals
so I hope you've uh enjoyed this video
and that you've learned something thank
you very much for watching